字幕翻译/压制：旋火
视频来源：youtu.be/xlPO0PKP4Fs
原视频发布日期：20190719
原作者名：Everyday Astronaut
- Hi, it's me, Tim Dodd, the Everyday Astronaut.
- 嗨 我是Tim Dodd 每日宇航员
It's been 50 years since Neil Armstrong famously stepped off the footpad of an Apollo Lunar Lander
距离尼尔阿姆斯特朗从阿波罗月球着陆器的脚垫上著名地走下已经有50年了
and onto a new celestial body for the first time in human history.
在人类历史上首次探访别的天体
And once he was safely standing on the surface of the moon
而当他刚安全地站到月球表面上时
he spoke perhaps some of the most famous words of all time.
他说了一些也许有史以来最有名的话
- [Neil Armstrong] It's one small step for man, one giant leap for mankind.
-  [尼尔阿姆斯特朗]这是我个人的一个小步 (但却是)人类的一大步
- But something about this always confused me.
- 可这件事总是困扰着我
I mean, sure, the step off of the lunar lander's 91 centimeter footpad was a nice easy and small step,
没错 走下登月舱的91厘米脚垫是一个很方便的一小步
but the step just before that was actually enormous.
但在那之前的一步则很巨大
I'm talking about this.
我说的是这个
The huge gap between the last rung of the ladder and the ground.
最后一个梯级与地面之间的巨大差距
I mean why on the moon is that gap so huge?
为什么在月球上会有这么大的差距？
Isn't it dangerous to require an astronaut to jump down onto the surface
要求宇航员跳下到表面是不是很危险
and then have to jump back up?
甚至还要再向上跳回来
The lunar lander's ladder had nine rungs,
登月舱的梯子有九个梯级
all spaced out at 22.8 centimeters apart from each other.
它们的间隔都是22.8厘米
But the gap between the last rung and the ground
但最后一个梯级与地面之间的空隙
was about three times that, at a whopping 76 centimeters.
大约是之前的三倍 高达76厘米
So really the ladder wasn't missing one rung,
实话说 这梯子不只是缺了一级
it was missing two.
是缺了两级
I mean, sure, the gravity's only one sixth that of Earth's,
没错 月球重力只有地球的六分之一
but wouldn't it have been so much safer if there was even just one more rung
但哪怕只是多一级梯子都安全很多
that closed that gap up just a little.
只要少一点空隙都好
So today we're gonna look into
那么我们今天来看看
why NASA and the lunar lander's manufacturer Grumman chose a ladder of this length.
为什么NA​​SA和登月器的制造商格鲁曼公司选择这个长度的梯子
We'll then talk about all the design considerations of the hardware,
然后 我们将讨论硬件的所有设计考虑
the unknown conditions of the lunar surface itself,
月面本身的未知的条件
and the astronauts who were basically just too smooth of pilots
还是说作为驾驶员的宇航员们都太熟练了
to get the ladder's last rung any closer to the surface of the moon.
不需要多余的那一级梯子来靠近月表
Lets get started.
让我们开始吧
- [Announcer] Three, two, one, liftoff!
-  [播音员]三 二 一 起飞
(energetic instrumental music)
（能量器乐）
- [Neil] It's one small step for man.
-  [尼尔]这是对人类的一个小步
- On May 25th, 1961,
- 在1961年5月25日
President John F. Kennedy announced his goal
约翰肯尼迪总统宣布了他的目标
of putting humans on the moon by the end of the decade to Congress.
跟国会说 在十年内把人类送到月球
At the time of this historic and ambitious announcement,
在这个历史性的雄心勃勃的通告发生之时
the U.S. had exactly 15 minutes and 22 seconds of human space flight experience
美国恰好只有15分22秒的载人航天经验
with just one suborbital launch under their belt.
而且只是一次亚轨道的经验
By the way, I should probably mention that Kennedy's speech in front of Congress
顺便说一句 肯尼迪在国会前的讲话
is not the famous We choose to go to the moon speech.
不是那个著名的 我们选择登月 的讲话
That happened over a year later at Rice Stadium in Houston.
这事发生在国会讲话的一年之后 在休斯敦的赖斯体育场
But the point is this insanely ambitious goal almost immediately put a lot of things in motion.
但问题是这种疯狂雄心勃勃的目标导致很多东西很快开始(同时)做
A tsunami of engineering ensued.
工程的海啸接踵而至
I mean so much so,
(展开)太多工作的话
sometimes it feels like the left hand didn't know what the right hand was doing.
感觉就像左手不知右手
One item that almost immediately began development was the lunar lander itself.
其中一个立刻开始研发的项目是月球着陆器
In July 1962, 11 companies were asked to submit proposals for a lunar lander.
1962年7月 11家公司被要求提交月球着陆器的计划
Grumman won the contract and began to design mock-ups as early as 1963.
格鲁曼公司赢得了合同 并早在1963年开始设计实体模型
Wait, what's all this have to do with a ladder?
等等 这些和梯子有啥关系
Well, hold up, I'm setting up a story here
稳住 我要把这里的(背景)故事说完
and to me, these stories are half the fun, these little fun nuggets of history.
有一半的成份是这些故事蕴含着历史的乐趣
But this particular bit of history is one of the key reasons why the ladder is the wrong length.
但是这段历史是解释梯子长度问题的关键所在
Grumman was building a lander intended to land on a surface that we knew literally nothing about.
格鲁曼公司正在建造的着陆器需要着陆在一种我们一无所知的表面上
This is understandable when the only data we had at the time
这是可以理解的 我们当时唯一的数据
was from the orbiters taking footage from the ranger missions.
是从绕月轨道器 徘徊者系列任务那里得到的
And before that, we just had ground based telescopes here on Earth.
而在这之前 只是靠地面的望远镜
Well, I guess actually Ranger 6 through 9 actually recorded footage all the way up until impact,
好吧 其实徘徊者6号到9号撞月前拍下的连续镜头
resulting in some footage with an impressive resolution of .3 meters.
带来了许多分辨率高达0.3米的影像
But, we still had almost no idea of what the surface of the moon was actually like.
但是我们仍未知道那时的月亮的表面如何
It wouldn't be until June 2nd, 1966,
直到1966年6月2日
before the U.S. would soft land surveyor one on the moon,
美国的勘测者号在月球软着陆
some four months after the Soviet Union landed Luna 9.
差不多是苏联的月球9号着陆4个月后
This would be the first time there'd be any data available to the U.S. about the composition of the moon's surface.
这也是美国第一次有了能了解月球表面构成的数据
And even so, it was quite limited.
即使如此 这也是非常有限的
This means during the first three years of development of the lunar lander,
这意味着在最初三年的月球着陆器的开发
there were countless question marks.
有无数的问题
Many scientists thought the surface might be so soft and powdery,
许多科学家认为表面可能是如此柔软 粉状的
it might swallow a spacecraft or people entirely on the surface,
它可能让人或者航天器完全陷入
sinking them so deep they wouldn't be able to get out.
以至于无法逃脱
While NASA was busy sending spacecraft after spacecraft to observe the moon,
虽然NASA正忙着把飞船发去观测月球
Grumman was deep in development of the lunar lander.
格鲁门公司则在深入地开发月球着陆器
The first couple years saw a lot of changes,
开发的前几年 方案就发生了很大变化
including things like going from five legs to four legs,
像是把五条腿改成四条腿
from a round cockpit to more of a polyhedral shape,
球形的座舱改成多面体的
and even going from a round hatch to a square hatch.
甚至还有把圆形舱门改成方形的
Oh by the way, that round hatch led to astronauts really struggling to get back into the spacecraft,
顺便说下 圆形舱门让宇航员很难返回航天器
so Grumman switched to a square version to help make egress and ingress that much easier.
所以格鲁曼改成了方门的方案 方便出入
This is also around the same time that Grumman was playing around with using a rope instead of a ladder,
与此同时 格鲁曼公司也在使用绳子而非梯子
which astronauts found to actually be impossible,
而宇航员发现使用绳子是极度困难的
and despite them using a peter pan pulley system which would simulate one sixth gravity.
尽管他们已经使用了 彼得潘 那样的滑轮系统 来模拟六分之一重力
So Grumman opted for a ladder down the front leg of the lunar lander.
于是格鲁曼公司选择了在着陆器的前腿下安装梯子
But even with something as simple as a ladder,
即使是梯子这般简单的东西
weight was an enormous factor.
重量也是大问题
I mean, after all, for each kilogram landed on the surface of the moon,
毕竟(发射)着陆到月球上的1kg质量
it takes about 400 kilograms of rocket to launch from Earth.
就需要大概400kg的火箭质量
This means Grumman went to great lengths to cut weight
这意味着格鲁曼公司费了九牛二虎之力 以减轻重量
including ditching seats and using lightweight golden kapton foil for insulation,
包括不用座椅和使用轻的金色聚酰亚胺薄膜作绝缘材料
but it also means the ladder, like all things,
于是梯子也一样
needed to be extremely lightweight.
也需要极端减重
For example, I think my favorite thing to think about is
例如 我最喜欢去思考的是
how if the lunar lander were standing on its own legs here on Earth,
如果登月舱在地球上用着陆腿支撑
it would've likely collapsed under its own weight
会因为他们自身的质量而倒塌
because those legs weren't meant for Earth's gravity.
因为那些腿并不是按照地球引力的标准设计的
They were only designed to handle the moon's weaker gravity.
而是按照较弱的月球引力设计的
And the same thing goes for the ladder.
对于梯子也是一样
If we were to try to ascend the ladder, the actual ladder, here on Earth,
如果我们在地球上试图登上那个梯子
it would've likely broken because it's not meant to handle Earth's gravity.
很可能它会因为地球引力更大的情况而坏掉
So they made it as lightweight as possible,
因此 他们把梯子做得尽量地轻
and only capable of handling one sixth gravity.
这样就只能应付六分之一的重力
But weight likely isn't the main reason why the ladder stopped short of the surface.
但是重量并非最后一级距离表面较远的主要原因
For this, we need to look at the landing gear the ladder is affixed to.
对于这一点 我们需要看看贴着梯子的那个起落架
The landing gear were designed to absorb the energy of impact
起落架被设计用来吸收碰撞能量
and keep the LEM(Lunar Excursion Module) from toppling over.
并防止登月舱翻倒
Grumman engineers were incredibly concerned with the LEM tipping over,
格鲁门公司的工程师们非常关心登月舱的翻倒问题
so a significant amount of work went into the design of the landing gear.
因此起落架的设计花费了不少工作
The landing gear was so vital that after the command module on the lunar excursion module undocked,
起落架是如此重要 在登月舱和指令舱分离时
the command module pilot was instructed to visually inspect all four legs
指令舱的驾驶员会被命令进行着陆腿的目视检查
to make sure they were properly deployed from their stowed position.
以确保他们正确地从(之前的)折叠状态展开
A leg that wasn't properly locked in place would've been an immediate abort.
如果着陆腿没有锁到正确的位置 任务就会马上终止
But fortunately, none of them failed to deploy.
不过幸运的是 没有一次发生过这样的情况
One interesting design consideration was the invention of a single use shock absorber.
一个有趣的设计考虑是一次性减震器的发明
NASA and Grumman developed a crushable honeycomb aluminum cartridge,
NASA和格鲁曼公司研制了一种可压碎的蜂窝状铝筒
otherwise known as a crush core.
也被称为粉碎芯
There was a great concern about using hydraulics in the landing gear
如果在起落架上使用液压装置
and fear that they could leak and leave a landing leg unusable.
一旦液体泄漏 可能会导致着陆腿无法使用
So, for simplicity's sake, they went with the crush core which is basically just a set of cartridges
因此 为了简单起见 他们使用了粉碎芯 基本上是一组填充物
made of aluminum that either compress or stretch to provide smooth and reliable resistance.
由铝做成的 以提供平滑和可靠的拉力或压力
This technology is still used today for certain applications.
这种技术至今仍在特定领域使用
Actually, SpaceX has crush core in the landing struts of their Falcon 9 rockets.
实际上 SpaceX的猎鹰9号着陆腿里就有这样的结构
If the hydraulic shock absorbers bottom out,
如果液压减震器失灵了
they have additional travel in the single use crush core.
还能使用粉碎芯的额外行程(来减震)
This was very obvious on Thaicom 8,
在Thaicom 8任务中很明显
which launched and landed on May 27th, 2016.
这是发生在2016年5月27日的任务 同日发射同日降落
The booster had a little bit of a rough landing,
一级火箭的降落有点粗暴
resulting in one of the landing legs eating into the crush core
导致其中一个着陆腿使用了粉碎核心
which made the booster stand lopsided.
使得一级火箭站得有点倾斜
By some miracle, the booster made it all the way back home,
某种奇迹之下 一级火箭一路拖回了家
despite some really, really close calls.
尽管有好几次差点掉水了
(laidback music)
（悠闲的音乐）
But back to the lunar lander.
话题回到登月舱
Its legs could absorb a large amount of impact velocity.
它的着陆腿能吸收大量的冲击速度
And due to their crush core absorbers,
得益于其粉碎核心这种(特殊)减震器
they did not rebound like a traditional hydraulic absorber.
它们不会像传统的液压减震器那样反弹
They just compressed and then they stayed in that position.
它们压缩之后就会在原地停下
They were designed to handle up to three meters per second of vertical velocity with zero horizontal velocity,
设计上 它们能承受3m/s的垂直速度和0m/s的水平速度
or up to 2.1 meters per second with 1.2 meters per second of horizontal velocity,
或者是2.1m/s的垂直速度和1.2m/s的水平速度
which they could handle very reliably.
在这个限度以内 可靠性很好
Now since NASA didn't know how much the shock absorbers would stroke or compress,
因为NASA并不知道减震器行程会有多少
and they were unsure of how deep into the lunar surface the LEM might sink,
而且他们也不知道月表会塌陷多少
they didn't want the ladder attached to the movable part of the strut
他们不想让梯子贴在着陆腿的可移动部分上面
and potentially hinder any movement.
这会阻碍着陆腿的活动
As a matter of fact, NASA assumed the struts would travel a lot more than they did.
事实上 NASA给着陆腿留了很大的伸缩量
Come to find out, two factors prevented them from actually traveling that much,
最后发现 两个因素减少了着陆腿的伸缩量
the pilots' skills and the surface of the moon's ability to absorb energy.
驾驶员的技能和月表吸收能量的能力
That's right.
没错
The pilots were in a sense maybe too gentle with the LEM and they all landed so stinking softly,
驾驶员对待登月舱非常温柔 他们着陆得如此轻柔
there was hardly any perceivable travel on the legs.
着陆腿几乎没有发生伸缩
But then again, there were so many unknown variables.
不过话说回来 面对未知
NASA was playing this whole thing extremely safe.
NASA希望(着陆)这件事非常安全
The astronauts were instructed to cut the engine
宇航员们被要求关闭引擎
when one of three 1.5 meter long lunar surface sensing probes made contact with the surface.
当3个1.5米长的月表探头和月表发生接触时
You've probably heard them make that contact call out.
你可能听他们说过这样的 接触 呼号
[奥尔德林] 接触灯亮
好的。发动机停止。
姿态控制组件(Attitude Control Assembly) - 停止。
[阿姆斯特朗] 停止。
[奥尔德林] 模式控制 - 都为自动。
下降级发动机指令手动控制 - 关闭。
发动机装置 - 关闭。
注：space.stackexchange.com/questions/10330/what-was-the-procedure-to-stop-the-descent-engine-on-the-apollo-11-lem
输入413指令。
This was intended to not only help
这样做 不仅是为了
prevent the engine from kicking up too much debris and dust for visibility and hole puncture concerns,
防止发动机吹起太多的碎屑和灰尘 影响能见度或者破坏地表
but it's also because the engine had engine thrust decay.
也是因为发动机有推力衰减
This is where even after successful shutdown of the engine,
即使在发动机停机成功后
there's still some residual pressure that can last anywhere from half a second to a few seconds.
其仍有半秒到数秒的时间保持一定的推力
All rocket engines have this.
所有火箭发动机都有这个问题
Fun side note,
有趣地是
this little bit of extra thrust decay went unnoticed on the test stand
在试车台上 额外的推力衰减往往被忽略
when SpaceX upgraded their Merlin engine between flights two and three of their Falcon 1 rocket.
当SpaceX在猎鹰1号火箭的第二次和第三次之间升级了他们的梅林发动机
After safe separation,
安全分离后
additional thrust decay led to a collision of the first and second stage,
额外的推力衰减导致了第一级和第二级之间的碰撞
causing a loss of the vehicle.
导致发射失败
The Apollo commander were intended to cut the engine at 1.5 meters in altitude,
阿波罗计划的指令长们被要求在1.5米高度关闭发动机
which would've been the right height to touchdown at a safe velocity,
可以让它以正确的高度 安全的速度触地
and compress the legs enough based on what NASA thought would be an adequate amount.
与此同时让着陆腿压缩在一个NASA认为是安全的范围之内
But despite all this,
但是 除此之外
all six landings had very different actual impact velocities.
6次着陆都有着不同的冲击速度
Neil Armstrong gave Apollo 11 the softest touchdown
尼尔阿姆斯特朗参与的阿波罗11号任务着陆最柔软
with a vertical velocity of .54 meters per second.
垂直速度仅0.54m/s
Apollo 17 was the next softest at .91 meters per second.
其次是阿波罗17号的0.91m/s
Apollo 14 was next, at .94 meters per second.
然后是阿波罗14号的0.94m/s
Then Apollo 12, at 1 meter per second.
阿波罗12号的1m/s
Apollo 16 at 1.7 meters per second.
阿波罗16号的1.7m/s
And lastly, Apollo 15's commander David Scott finally gave her the beans at 2.07 meters per second.
最后 阿波罗15号的指令长戴维斯科特达到了2.07m/s
But that still well within the operational range to the legs.
但这仍在操作范围之中
And now a big concern was having the descent engine coming in contact with a lunar surface.
还有个问题是下降级发动机会和月表发生接触
And despite Apollo 15 carrying the additional mass of the lunar rover vehicle,
尽管阿波罗15号有着携带月球车的附加质量
having a 25 centimeter nozzle extension on the descent engine,
下降级发动机有着(相比之前任务)长了的25厘米的喷嘴
landing on the steepest lunar slope of 11 degrees.
进行了达到11度倾斜 也是最陡峭的降落
And despite the nozzle actually buckling,
尽管喷嘴实际上有点弯曲变形
the nozzle still didn't actually come in contact with the surface at all.
喷嘴仍未与表面有任何接触
The buckling of the nozzle was due to a buildup of pressure
喷嘴的弯曲变形是因为
from firing the nozzle so close to the surface,
过于接近地面的点火造成的压力的聚集
and not from coming in contact with the surface itself.
而不是和表面发生的接触
But another factor that was later accounted for on why the stress didn't compress that much,
(除了驾驶员的技巧)关于(着陆)压力没有这么大的另一个原因则是
was the fact that due to the moon's somewhat powdery surface
较为粉末状的月表
the surface itself would actually absorb around 80% of the impact velocity.
吸收了差不多80%的冲击速度
And this is perhaps why the landing legs compressed so much less than they had planned,
这也是为什么着陆腿的压缩远小于之前预计的
leaving the final rung higher than nominal.
(而这所有的一切)导致最后一级梯子比正常情况下的要高
Okay, so basically the moral of the story is
这个故事想表达的是
landing on the moon was a big fat question mark with the Apollo program.
阿波罗计划中的登月那部分问题重重
NASA took the most conservative approach to as many things as possible,
NASA采取了最保守的方法 以尽可能多的冗余
including fail proof shock absorbers,
包括未能证明自己的减震器
additional thermal protection on the landing legs,
着陆腿上额外的热保护层
big fat landing pads,
较大的着陆脚垫
and contact probes to name a few.
还有接触探头等等
Suffice to say they didn't wanna make the ladder any longer than necessary
只是说 他们确实是不想要梯子
and potentially hinder movement of the landing gear.
超出必要的长度导致对着陆腿运动潜在的影响
So assuming things went as planned and the shock absorbers went deep enough,
假设计划和现实一致 减震器也没有这么夸张
the ladder would've been a nice and easy step.
梯子(的最后一级)跨过去(也会比现在)容易很多
But all this said, the final step still worried some astronauts.
尽管如此 最后一步还是对一些宇航员造成了不少困扰
The commanders were actually trained to immediately attempt to jump back up to the bottom rung,
指令长在训练中被要求尝试立刻跳回最后一级梯子
after initial descent down the ladder.
在第一次触地之后
This way the pilot who is still inside the LEM could assist if there is any struggle to make that large gap.
这样的话 如果跳下这么大的空隙造成了任何问题 还在登月舱里的驾驶员就能帮助他
Neil actually commented on this before he stepped off the lander's pad.
尼尔在他走下登月舱的脚垫之前还对此作出了评论
[阿姆斯特朗] - 好的。我刚检查了下，呃 -
回到之前那个第一步，巴兹。这有点 -
没有那么容易塌陷，但还是需要回来下。
[休斯顿] - 好的我们收到了
[阿姆斯特朗] - 这需要跳那么一小步。
Different astronauts had different experiences with the ladder.
不同的宇航员有着不同的爬梯体验
Such as Jim Irwin saying the ladder was a real struggle.
如吉姆欧文说 梯子真是个麻烦事
And 170 centimeter tall Pete Conrad saying.
而身高170cm的皮特康拉德说
[康拉德] - 喔！老哥，这对尼尔来讲可能是一小步，
但对我而言有点太大了。
So to summarize, the final rung height was a topic for much debate.
总结下 最后一级梯子的高度是个争议性话题
But with all the unknown variables,
但是面对未知
a bounty out there for every single kilogram to be shaved from the vehicle,
也是为了节省载具的质量
and figuring jumping up and down in one sixth gravity would make ascent and descent much easier.
而六分之一重力下的跳跃又会使得这一切变得容易
They also didn't know how much the lunar surface would absorb energy,
还有就是他们不知道月表会吸收多少能量
so NASA left the bottom rung at it's final gap of 76 centimeters,
所以最后NASA把最后一级梯子留了76cm的高度
from the bottom of the ladder to the top of the landing pad.
也就是梯子的底部到着陆脚垫的距离
Or maybe NASA could've just done
或者NASA只需要
what the Soviet Union planned to do with their LK Lunar Lander, and just used a hinge ladder.
像苏联计划对他们的LK月球着陆器做的那样 使用一个铰链式的(伸缩)梯子
So what do you think?
所以你怎么看？
Did I help answer all your questions about
why the lunar lander's ladder was the height that it was?
Let me know if you have any other questions about this topic or about the Apollo program
or just rocket science in general.
And stay tuned, cause I have a lot of really awesome videos coming up.
I owe a huge thank you to my patreon supporters for helping make content like this possible.
So if you wanna help, maybe add your voice to these scripts
or help catch airs before these videos come out,
or even just talk with other space fans,
consider becoming a patreon supporter by going to patreon.com/everydayastronaut
where you'll gain exclusive access to our Reddit,
our Discord channel, and some exclusive livestreams as well.
Thank you.
And while you're online, be sure and check out my webstore
where you can find things like this shirt,
which by the way is almost sold out.
And that's because we do runs of shirts now so the quality's a lot higher.
There's also custom tags and custom packaging.
But there's also tons of things in this store that are kinda constantly,
we're trying to keep up with all these things like Grid Fin Not-A-Coasters and mugs and hats,
and lots of other fun stuff.
So, be sure and check that out.
And while you're on there,
click on the music tab where you can listen to my music on Spotify and on iTunes,
and also a playlist right here on YouTube as well.
Add it to a playlist of summer and let me know what you think.
Thanks everybody, that's gonna do it for me.
I'm Tim Dodd, the everyday astronaut,
(laidback music)
（悠闲的音乐）